So there are lands few and far between on Earth itself
الأراضي الصالحة لعيش الإنسان على كوكبنا
that are hospitable to humans by any measure,
قليلة ومتباعدة.
but survive we have.
ولكن علينا أن نحيا.
Our primitive ancestors, when they found their homes and livelihood endangered,
وعندما أدرك أسلافنا الأوائل أن مساكنهم ومعيشتهم في خطر،
they dared to make their way into unfamiliar territories
غامروا بإيجاد طريقهم وسط بيئات غريبة
in search of better opportunities.
بحثاً عن فرص أفضل للعيش.
And as the descendants of these explorers,
وكأحفاد لأولئك المستكشفين،
we have their nomadic blood coursing through our own veins.
فإن دماء الترحال تجري في عروقنا.
But at the same time,
لكن في نفس الوقت،
distracted by our bread and circuses
فنحن مشغولون بلقمة العيش ومصاعب الحياة
and embroiled in the wars that we have waged on each other,
ومتورطون في الحروب التي نشنها فيما بيننا،
it seems that we have forgotten this desire to explore.
يبدو وكأننا نسينا حب الاستكشاف.
We, as a species, we're evolved uniquely
وقد تطورنا كنوع بشكل فريد
for Earth, on Earth, and by Earth,
من أجل الأرض وفوقها وبها،
and so content are we with our living conditions
ونحن سعداء جدا بظروف عيشنا
that we have grown complacent and just too busy
لدرجة أننا كبرنا مع حس بالرضى لكننا فقط مشغولون جدا
to notice that its resources are finite,
لدرجة أننا لم نلاحظ أن مواردنا محدودة،
and that our Sun's life is also finite.
وأن عمر شمسنا أيضا محدود.
While Mars and all the movies made in its name
في حين أن المريخ وكل الأفلام المصنوعة باسمه
have reinvigorated the ethos for space travel,
قد أعادت بعث الحلم البشري بالسفر عبر الفضاء،
few of us seem to truly realize that our species' fragile constitution
فإن القليل منا فقط أدركوا بأن تكويننا الهش كمخلوقات
is woefully unprepared for long duration journeys into space.
غير مستعد تماماً للرحلات الفضائية الطويلة.
Let us take a trek to your local national forest
دعونا نتوجه إلى غابتكم الوطنية المحلية
for a quick reality check.
من أجل دراسة سريعة للواقع.
So just a quick show of hands here:
سأطلب منكم رفع أيديكم للإجابة:
how many of you think you would be able to survive in this lush wilderness
كم منكم يعتقد بأنه قادر على البقاء حياً في هذه البرية الخضراء
for a few days?
لبضعة أيام؟
Well, that's a lot of you.
حسناً، أنتم كثر.
How about a few weeks?
ماذا عن بضعة أسابيع؟
That's a decent amount.
هذه نتيجة محترمة.
How about a few months?
ماذا عن بضعة أشهر؟
That's pretty good too.
هذا جيد أيضاً.
Now, let us imagine that this local national forest
دعونا نتخيل بأن الغابة الوطنية المحلية
experiences an eternal winter.
تعرف شتاء أبديا.
Same questions: how many of you think you would be able to survive for a few days?
نفس الأسئلة: كم منكم يعتقد بأنه قادر على البقاء حياً لبضعة أيام؟
That's quite a lot.
هذا كثير جداً.
How about a few weeks?
ماذا عن بضعة أسابيع؟
So for a fun twist, let us imagine that the only source of water available
ومن أجل المزاح، دعونا نتخيل بأن المصدر الوحيد للماء
is trapped as frozen blocks miles below the surface.
محتجز ككتل مجمدة علي بعد مئات الأمتار تحت السطح.
Soil nutrients are so minimal that no vegetation can be found,
وأن مغذيات التربة قليلة بشكل لا يمكن معه العثور على نباتات،
and of course hardly any atmosphere exists to speak of.
وبالطبع لا يوجد غلاف جوي يذكر.
Such examples are only a few of the many challenges we would face
وهذه الأمثلة هي غيض من فيض للتحديات التي سنواجها
on a planet like Mars.
على كوكب كالمريخ.
So how do we steel ourselves for voyages whose destinations are so far removed
فكيف نعد أنفسنا لرحلات أبعد
from a tropical vacation?
من عطلة بالمناطق الاستوائية؟
Will we continuously ship supplies from Planet Earth?
هل سنشحن المؤونة من الأرض بشكل منتظم؟
Build space elevators, or impossible miles of transport belts
نصنع مصاعد فضائية أو آلاف الكيلومترات من أحزمة النقل المستحيلة
that tether your planet of choice to our home planet?
والتي تصل بين كوكبنا الأم والكوكب الذي اخترتموه؟
And how do we grow things like food that grew up on Earth like us?
وكيف سنزرع أشياء مثل المحاصيل التي تنمو على الأرض مثلنا؟
But I'm getting ahead of myself.
لكن ربما أني استبقت الأمور.
In our species' journey to find a new home under a new sun,
ففي رحلة فصيلنا بحثاً عن منزل جديد تحت شمس جديدة،
we are more likely than not going to be spending much time
قد نستغرق وقتاً أكبر
in the journey itself,
في الرحلة نفسها،
in space,
في الفضاء،
on a ship, a hermetic flying can,
على متن مركبة، وفي علبة طائرة محكمة الإغلاق،
possibly for many generations.
وعلى الأرجح لعدة أجيال.
The longest continuous amount of time that any human has spent in space
فأطول مدة قضاها الإنسان في الفضاء
is in the vicinity of 12 to 14 months.
هي حوالي 12 و14 شهراً.
From astronauts' experiences in space,
وبفضل تجارب رواد الفضاء
we know that spending time in a microgravity environment
نعرف أنه قضاء وقت في بيئة ذات جاذبية مضمحلة
means bone loss, muscle atrophy, cardiovascular problems,
يعني هشاشة العظام وضمور العضلات ومشاكل القلب والأوعية الدموية،
among many other complications
والعديد من المشاكل الصحية الأخرى
that range for the physiological to the psychological.
ابتداءً من مشاكل جسدية إلى مشاكل نفسية.
And what about macrogravity,
فماذا عن الجاذبية الشديدة،
or any other variation in gravitational pull
أو عن أي متغير في قوة الجاذبية
of the planet that we find ourselves on?
للكوكب الذي وجدنا عليه أنفسنا؟
In short, our cosmic voyages will be fraught with dangers
وباختصار، فإن رحلاتنا الفضائية ستكون محفوفة بالمخاطر
both known and unknown.
سواء المعروفة منها أو المجهولة.
So far we've been looking to this new piece of mechanical technology
دائما ما كنا نبحث عن تلك القطعة الجديدة من التقنية الميكانيكية
or that great next generation robot
أو عن ذاك الجيل القادم من الآليين الرائعين
as part of a lineup to ensure our species safe passage in space.
كجزء من سلسلة ستضمن لنا عبوراً آمناً للفضاء.
Wonderful as they are, I believe the time has come
ورغم روعتهم، أعتقد أنه حان الوقت
for us to complement these bulky electronic giants
كي ندعم عمالقة التقنية تلك
with what nature has already invented:
بما اخترعته الطبيعة بالفعل:
the microbe,
الميكروب،
a single-celled organism that is itself a self-generating, self-replenishing,
كائن وحيد الخلية هو في حد ذاته ذاتي التوليد ومكتفي ذاتياً،
living machine.
إنه آلة حية.
It requires fairly little to maintain,
وهي بحاجة للقليل للبقاء على قيد الحياة،
offers much flexibility in design
وتقدم ليونة أكبر في تصميمها
and only asks to be carried in a single plastic tube.
ولا تتطلب سوى أن توضع بأنبوب بلاستيكي صغير
The field of study that has enabled us to utilize the capabilities of the microbe
ويعرف المجال العلمي الذي سمح لنا باستعمال قدرات الميكروب
is known as synthetic biology.
بالبيولوجيا التركيبية.
It comes from molecular biology, which has given us antibiotics, vaccines
وهو متفرع عن علم الأحياء الجزيئي الذي قدم لنا المضادات الحيوية والأمصال
and better ways to observe the physiological nuances
وطرق أفضل لمراقبة الاختلافات الوظائفية
of the human body.
للجسم البشري.
Using the tools of synthetic biology,
وباستعمال أدوات البيولوجيا التركيبية،
we can now edit the genes of nearly any organism,
يمكننا تقريباً استعراض جينات أي كائن حي،
microscopic or not,
سواء كان مجهرياً أو لا،
with incredible speed and fidelity.
بسرعة ودقة كبيرتين.
Given the limitations of our man-made machines,
ونظراً لمحدودية قدرات الآلات بشرية الصنع،
synthetic biology will be a means for us to engineer not only our food,
ستكون البيولوجيا التركيبية وسيلة نستعملها لهندسة ليس فقط محاصيلنا
our fuel and our environment,
وكذا وقودنا وبيئتنا،
but also ourselves
بل أيضاً أنفسنا
to compensate for our physical inadequacies
لتعويض نقائصنا الجسمانية
and to ensure our survival in space.
وضمان بقاءنا أحياء في الفضاء.
To give you an example
ولأقدم لكم مثالاً
of how we can use synthetic biology for space exploration,
عن كيف يمكننا استعمال البيولوجيا التركيبية لاستكشاف الفضاء،
let us return to the Mars environment.
دعونا نعود إلى بيئة المريخ.
The Martian soil composition is similar to that of Hawaiian volcanic ash,
تتشابه تركيبة التربة في المريخ بالرماد البركاني في هاواي،
with trace amounts of organic material.
مع نسبة ضئيلة من المواد العضوية.
Let's say, hypothetically,
ودعونا نقول، افتراضاً،
what if martian soil could actually support plant growth
ماذا لو كانت تربة المريخ قادرة فعلاً على دعم نمو النبات
without using Earth-derived nutrients?
دون استخدام المغذيات المشتقة من الأرض؟
The first question we should probably ask is,
السؤال الذي ينبغي علينا طرحه على الأرجح هو،
how would we make our plants cold-tolerant?
كيف يمكننا جعل نباتاتنا تتحمل البرد؟
Because, on average, the temperature on Mars
لأن متوسط درجة الحرارة على المريخ
is a very uninviting negative 60 degrees centigrade.
غير مبشرة للغاية حيث تصل سالب 60 درجة مئوية.
The next question we should ask is,
السؤال التالي هو،
how do we make our plants drought-tolerant?
كيف يمكننا جعل نباتاتنا تتحمل الجفاف؟
Considering that most of the water that forms as frost
باعتبار أن معظم المياه المتكونة من الجليد
evaporates more quickly than I can say the word "evaporate."
تتبخر أسرع من نطقي لكلمة "تبخر"
Well, it turns out we've already done things like this.
الواقع، لقد اتضح أننا قمنا بالفعل بأشياء من هذا القبيل.
By borrowing genes for anti-freeze protein from fish
وذلك باستعارة جينات البروتين المضاد للتجمد من الأسماك
and genes for drought tolerance from other plants like rice
وجينات تحمل الجفاف من نباتات أخرى كالأرز
and then stitching them into the plants that need them,
وبعدها نزرعها في النباتات المحتاجة لها،
we now have plants that can tolerate most droughts and freezes.
وحالياً نملك نباتات تتحمل أقصى درجات الجفاف و البرد.
They're known on Earth as GMOs,
وتسمى على الأرض GMOs
or genetically modified organisms,
أي الكائنات المعدلة وراثياً،
and we rely on them to feed all the mouths of human civilization.
ونعتمد عليها في إطعام كافة أفواه الحضارة البشرية.
Nature does stuff like this already,
الطبيعة تقوم بأشياء كهذه بالفعل،
without our help.
دون مساعدة منا.
We have simply found more precise ways to do it.
ولكننا وجدنا فقط طرق أدق للقيام بذلك.
So why would we want to change the genetic makeup of plants for space?
إذاً لما علينا تغيير تصميم جينات النباتات لتلائم الفضاء؟
Well, to not do so would mean needing to engineer
عدم القيام بذلك سيعني الحاجة إلى تجهيز
endless acres of land on an entirely new planet
هكتارات لا تنتهي من الأراضي على كوكب جديد بالكلية
by releasing trillions of gallons of atmospheric gasses
من خلال إطلاق مليارات الجالونات من غازات الغلاف الجوي
and then constructing a giant glass dome to contain it all.
وبناء قبة زجاجية ضخمة لاحتوائها جميعاً.
It's an unrealistic engineering enterprise
وهذا مشروع تصميمي غير واقعي
that quickly becomes a high-cost cargo transport mission.
سيتحول سريعاً إلى عملية نقل بضائع مكلفة جدا.
One of the best ways to ensure
إحدى أفضل الطرق لضمان
that we will have the food supplies and the air that we need
أننا سنتحصل على الإمدادت التي نحتاجها من الغذاء والهواء
is to bring with us organisms that have been engineered
هي باصطحابنا لكائنات حية مصممة وراثياً
to adapt to new and harsh environments.
لتتكيف مع العيش في بيئات جديدة وقاسية.
In essence, using engineered organisms to help us terraform a planet
في الواقع سنستخدم الكائنات المصممة وراثياً لمساعدتنا على استصلاح كوكب ما
both in the short and long term.
سواء على المدى القريب أو البعيد.
These organisms can then also be engineered to make medicine or fuel.
كما يمكن تصميم تلك الكائنات وراثياً لإنتاج الدواء أو الوقود.
So we can use synthetic biology to bring highly engineered plants with us,
إذاً، يمكننا استعمال البيولوجيا التركيبية لأخذ نباتات مصممة وراثيا معنا،
but what else can we do?
فما الذي يمكننا فعله أيضاً؟
Well, I mentioned earlier that we, as a species,
لقد أشرت من قبل أننا كنوع
were evolved uniquely for planet Earth.
تطورنا بشكل فريد لملاءمة كوكب الأرض.
That fact has not changed much in the last five minutes
وهذه الحقيقة لم تتغير كثيراً خلال الدقائق الخمس الأخيرة
that you were sitting here and I was standing there.
منذ جلوسكم في مقاعدكم ووقوفي هنا.
And so, if we were to dump any of us on Mars right this minute,
وعليه، إن نحن أرسلنا أحدنا إلى المريخ الآن،
even given ample food, water, air
ورغم تزويده بما يكفي من الغذاء والماء والهواء
and a suit,
وبذلة فضائية،
we are likely to experience very unpleasant health problems
سيواجه على الأرجح مشاكل صحية غير سارة
from the amount of ionizing radiation that bombards the surface
بسبب معدل الإشعاع المؤين الذي يقصف سطح
of planets like Mars that have little or nonexistent atmosphere.
كواكب كالمريخ والذي يملك غلاف جوي ضعيف أو منعدم.
Unless we plan to stay holed up underground
إلا إذا كنا نخطط للاختباء تحت السطح
for the duration of our stay on every new planet,
خلال مدة استوطاننا لكل كوكب جديد،
we must find better ways of protecting ourselves
سيكون علينا إيجاد طرق أفضل لحماية أنفسنا
without needing to resort to wearing a suit of armor
دون الحاجة لارتداء بذلة مصفحة
that weighs something equal to your own body weight,
لها نفس وزن أجسامكم،
or needing to hide behind a wall of lead.
أو الحاجة للاختباء خلف جدار رصاصي.
So let us appeal to nature for inspiration.
لذا دعونا نستوحي من الطبيعة.
Among the plethora of life here on Earth,
من بين الكائنات الكثيرة على الأرض،
there's a subset of organisms known as extremophiles,
هناك مجموعة فرعية تسمى أليفات الظروف القاسية،
or lovers of extreme living conditions,
أو محبات الظروف القاسية،
if you'll remember from high school biology.
إن كنتم تذكرون دروس علم الأحياء في الثانوية.
And among these organisms is a bacterium by the name of Deinococcus radiodurans.
ومن بين تلك الكائنات هناك بكتيريا تدعى دينوكوكوس راديودورانس
It is known to be able to withstand cold, dehydration, vacuum, acid,
وهي معروفة بقدرتها على تحمل البرد والجفاف والفراغ والحمض
and, most notably, radiation.
والأهم الإشعاع.
While its radiation tolerance mechanisms are known,
ورغم تعرفنا على الآليات التي تتحمل بها الإشعاع،
we have yet to adapt the relevant genes to mammals.
مازال علينا ملاءمة الجينات المعنية مع الثدييات.
To do so is not particularly easy.
والأمر ليس سهلاً للقيام بذلك.
There are many facets that go into its radiation tolerance,
لأن هناك العديد من الأبعاد التي تتدخل في تحملها للإشعاع،
and it's not as simple as transferring one gene.
وهذا الأمر ليس بسهولة تحويل جين واحد.
But given a little bit of human ingenuity
ولكن مع القليل من البراعة البشرية
and a little bit of time,
والقليل من الوقت،
I think to do so is not very hard either.
أعتقد أن القيام بذلك ليس بالأمر الصعب أيضاً.
Even if we borrow just a fraction of its ability to tolerate radiation,
حتى وإن اكتسبنا جزء صغير فقط من قدرتها على تحمل الإشعاع،
it would be infinitely better than what we already have,
سيكون أمرأ جيداً للغاية بالمقارنة مع ما نمتلكه الآن،
which is just the melanin in our skin.
ألا وهو صبغ الميلانين في جلدنا.
Using the tools of synthetic biology,
باستخدام أدوات البيولوجيا التركيبية،
we can harness Deinococcus radiodurans' ability
يمكننا اكتساب قدرة دينوكوكوس على تحمل الإشعاع
to thrive under otherwise very lethal doses of radiation.
والإزدهار في بيئة ذات جرعات إشعاعية قاتلة.
As difficult as it is to see,
رغم صعوبة إدراك ذلك،
homo sapiens, that is humans,
فإن الإنسان العاقل وهو البشر،
evolves every day,
يتطور كل يوم،
and still continues to evolve.
ومستمر في التطور.
Thousands of years of human evolution
فآلاف السنوات من التطور البشري
has not only given us humans like Tibetans,
لم تنتج لنا فقط أناس كالتبتيين،
who can thrive in low-oxygen conditions,
قادرين على العيش في بيئة منخفضة الأكسجين،
but also Argentinians, who can ingest and metabolize arsenic,
بل أيضا أرجنتينيين قادرين على هضم وأيض الزرنيخ،
the chemical element that can kill the average human being.
العنصر الكيميائي القادر على قتل الإنسان العادي.
Every day, the human body evolves by accidental mutations
ويتطور الجسم البشري في كل يوم بواسطة طفرات عرضية
that equally accidentally allow certain humans
تسمح بدورها عرضياً لبعض البشر
to persevere in dismal situations.
بأن يعيشوا في أوضاع مزرية.
But, and this is a big but,
لكن، مع خط تحت لكن،
such evolution requires two things that we may not always have,
تلك التطورات بحاجة إلى أمرين قد لا نتملكهما دائما،
or be able to afford,
أو نتمكن من التحكم فيهما،
and they are death and time.
وهما الموت والوقت.
In our species' struggle to find our place in the universe,
خلال نضالنا كنوع للبحث عن مكان لنا في الكون،
we may not always have the time necessary
قد لا نمتلك دائما الوقت الضروري
for the natural evolution of extra functions
للتطور الطبيعي لوظائف آخرى
for survival on non-Earth planets.
للبقاء أحياء على كواكب غير الأرض.
We're living in what E.O. Wilson has termed the age of gene circumvention,
نحن نعيش في ما اصطلح عليه إدوارد أوسبورن ويلسون بعصر التحايل على الجين،
during which we remedy our genetic defects like cystic fibrosis or muscular dystrophy
الذي نقوم فيه بمعالجة اختلالاتنا الجينية كالتليف الكيسي أو الضمور العضلي
with temporary external supplements.
بإضافات خارجية مؤقتة.
But with every passing day,
لكن بمرور كل يوم،
we approach the age of volitional evolution,
نقترب من عصر التطور الإرادي،
a time during which we as a species
الذي سنملك خلاله كنوع
will have the capacity to decide for ourselves our own genetic destiny.
القدرة على أن نقرر بأنفسنا مصيرنا الجيني.
Augmenting the human body with new abilities
فتحسين الجسم البشري بقدرات جديدة
is no longer a question of how,
لم تعد مسألة كيف،
but of when.
بل متى.
Using synthetic biology
استخدام البيولوجيا التركيبية
to change the genetic makeup of any living organisms,
لتغيير البنية الجينية لأي كائن حي،
especially our own,
خاصة جيناتنا،
is not without its moral and ethical quandaries.
لا تخلوا من المعضلات الأخلاقية.
Will engineering ourselves make us less human?
هل تصميمنا لأنفسنا جينيا سيجعلنا أقل إنسانية؟
But then again, what is humanity
لكن مرة أخرى، ما هي الإنسانية،
but star stuff that happens to be conscious?
سوى بقايا نجوم صادف أنها مدركة لما حولها؟
Where should human genius direct itself?
ما هو التوجه الذي على العبقرية الإنسانية اتخاذه؟
Surely it is a bit of a waste to sit back and marvel at it.
الأكيد أنه سيكون لا فائدة من الاكتفاء بالجلوس والنظر.
How do we use our knowledge
كيف نستعمل معرفتنا
to protect ourselves from the external dangers
لحماية أنفسنا من الأخطار الخارجية
and then protect ourselves from ourselves?
ومن ثم حماية أنفسنا من أنفسنا؟
I pose these questions
أناا أطرح هذه الأسئلة
not to engender the fear of science
ليس من أجل بث الخوف من العلوم
but to bring to light the many possibilities
لكن من أجل تسليط الضوء على الإمكانيات العديدة
that science has afforded and continues to afford us.
التي أتاحتها لنا العلوم وما زالت تتيحها لنا.
We must coalesce as humans to discuss and embrace the solutions
علينا كبشر أن نلتقي ونتحدث ونتبنى الحلول
not only with caution
ليس فقط بدافع الخوف
but also with courage.
لكن بشجاعة أيضاً.
Mars is a destination,
المريخ هو وجهة،
but it will not be our last.
لكنها ليست الأخيرة.
Our true final frontier is the line we must cross
حدودنا الأخيرة الحقيقية هي تلك التي علينا عبورها
in deciding what we can and should make of our species' improbable intelligence.
بتقريرنا ما يمكننا وما علينا فعله بالعبقرية الغير محتملة لأنواعنا.
Space is cold, brutal and unforgiving.
الفضاء بارد ومعاد ولا يرحم.
Our path to the stars will be rife with trials
طريقنا إلى النجوم سيكون محفوف بالتجارب
that will bring us to question not only who we are
ستدفعنا ليس فقط إلى التساءل عمن نحن
but where we will be going.
بل عن أين نحن ذاهبون.
The answers will lie in our choice to use or abandon the technology
وستكمن الأجوبة في اختيارنا لاستعمال أو التخلي عن التقنية
that we have gleaned from life itself,
التي التقطناها من الحياة نفسها،
and it will define us for the remainder of our term in this universe.
وستحدد هويتنا لما تبقى لنا من وقت في هذا الكون.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)